むった
(六太)お～っ！ここが
ジョンソン宇宙センター！
This is the Johnson Space Center!
広～っ！
It's huge...
ふふん｡このジョンソン
宇宙センターで働くスタッフは➡
Three thousand people work at the Johnson Space Center.
総勢3000人｡その大半は
科学者かエンジニアで➡
Half are scientists or engineers, and one hundred are astronauts.
さらに その中の100人が
宇宙飛行士！
アンタの弟 ヒビト･ナンバも
その１人ってわけよ｡
Your brother, Hibito Nanba, is one of those hundred.
(六太)ねえ 息つぎしてる？
Uh, did you breathe at all during that?
Hmm? Did you say something?
N-No... I must say that the aerospace center is certainly impressive!
え？いや～ ホント
さすが宇宙の本場だ！
ふふん｡
ひびと
ナサ
＜日々人の招きでＮＡＳＡを
なんば
訪れた私 南波六太は➡
After Hibito invited me to visit NASA, I, Nanba Mutta,
ついに聖地 ジョンソン
宇宙センタｰへの第一歩を記した＞
have finally taken my first step into the holy land, the Johnson Space Center.
＜ここに
数千万人の中から勝ち残った➡
This is the
final destination for those few, who were chosen amongst millions, to become astronauts.
選ばれし宇宙飛行士達がいる＞
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
#06 Et Cetera in My Head
If we must eliminate one...
たぬま
(田沼)どちらか１人を
落とすというのであれば➡
私は迷いなく
南波君を落とします｡
If I had to cut one of them...
I would immediately pick Nanba.
ほしか
(星加)何故です？南波君の方が
票が多かったはずですが｡
Why?
There were more votes for Nanba.
この２人は 英語力や
身体能力面においては➡
Both applicants easily pass the requirements for English and physical ability.
十分クリアできるレベルに
あります｡
問題は精神面です｡
The problem is on the psychological side.
南波君の精神面に 何か問題が
あるとは私は思いませんでしたが｡
I don't believe that Nanba had any issues
of the psychological kind.
シャンプー男だから？
ハハハ！泡立つらしいからねえ｡
Are you thinking of the shampoo story?
He can make a lot of bubbles...
いえ 実は私 南波君のことを
調べました｡➡
No, I actually did some research on Nanba.
彼は 前の会社を
クビになっています｡➡
He was fired from his previous job.
それも
上司に対する暴力が原因で｡
He apparently assaulted his supervisor.
おおっ！月面基地！
The Moon base!
この施設に
ヒビト達が滞在するの｡➡
This is where Hibito and the other astronauts will live.
月への移住計画の第一歩
ってわけね｡
It will be the first step on the way
to lunar colonization.
Amazing...
すんげえ！完成するとこうなる
のか！これは知らなかった｡
So this is how it will look when it's complete.
I had no idea.
おおっ！火星探査!!
Oh! A Mars Exploration Rover!
火星は 月とは比べ物に
ならないくらい遠いからね｡
Mars is much, much farther away than the moon.
一番早いロケットでも
片道で半年以上かかるわ｡
It's a six month, one-way trip using our fastest rocket.
なるほど～ やっぱ着陸の時は
この方式でいく計画なんだな｡
I see...
So that's how the rover looks, once it's landed.
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)セス
ヒビト達 ＣＥＳ５１のクルーは➡
Hibito and the other CES51 crew members
この時間 フィジカルトレーニング
の最中なのよ｡
usually train around this time.
ねえ ジェニファー｡
Say, Jennifer.
It looks like the others are jogging,
他のみんなは ジョギングで➡
日々人だけが
ダッシュに見えるんだけど｡
while Hibito is the only one sprinting.
ヒビトはいつも あんなもんよ｡
He's always that way.
あんたも兄貴なら
あれぐらい走れないとねえ｡
As his big brother, you'll need to be faster than he is.
カッコイイ ヒビト！
１周目からペース落ちてないよ！
Great stuff, Hibito!
Your second lap was just as fast your first!
そこは正確に言っとこうよ｡
｢２秒遅くなったわよ｣って｡
You should tell him the truth.
He was two seconds slower on the second lap.
≪ゴー！ゴー！≫
Go! Go!
サムライボーイ！
Go, Samurai Boy!
プッ！フフフ…今の聞いた？
サムライだって 日々人のこと｡
Did you hear that?
They called Hibito a samurai.
何よ？皆よく そう呼んでるわよ｡
ええっ？マジで!?
So? That's what everyone calls him.
Huh? Seriously?
Great!
グレイト！
ゴー！ゴー！
へえ…｡
Go! Go!
＜私はもう 心の中で
笑うしかなかった｡➡
I couldn't help
but to laugh on the inside.
あの日々人が侍だってぇ!?＞
They're calling Hibito a samurai?
Mike is samuraiing Ken.
＜｢侍｣と｢待つ｣をごっちゃに
していた あの日々人が＞
When he once mixed up the characters for "samurai" and "wait"?
Samurai Boy! Samurai Boy! Samurai Boy!
サムライボーイ！
ゴー！ゴー！ゴー！
《あのヤロー｡
何かオレを挑発してやがるな》
That bastard...
He's taunting me.
悪いが…オレは走らねえよ｡
Sorry, but I'm not running.
だって…見学だもの｡
After all,
I'm just a visitor.
Fifty-four...
(日々人)５４…５５…➡
Fifty-five...
５６…５７…｡
記録更新だ ヒビト｡
Fifty-six...
That's a new record, Hibito.
Fifty-seven...
５８…｡
おおっ まだいくっ！
Fifty-eight...
Oh, you're still going!
Fifty-nine...
５９…６０…６１…６２…｡
Sixty...
Sixty-one...
Sixty-two...
アスリートにでもなる気かよ
あのヤロー｡
Is he trying to become an athlete?
Sixty-three...
月面上じゃ ヒビトの体重は
１２キロもないのよ｡
On the moon,
Sixty-four...
Hibito will weigh fewer than twelve kilograms.
長期滞在ってなると 毎日最低
２時間は筋トレが必要なわけ｡➡
He has to lift weights two hours per day to prepare for his extended stay.
ヒビトのようなタイプは
長期ミッションに適してるのよ｡
People like Hibito are perfect for long missions.
さすがはサムライボーイだわ｡
That's the Samurai Boy for you.
《侍ねえ…》
Samurai, huh?
あと 宇宙じゃ時間の感覚って
いうのも大事なんだけどね｡
It's also critical to be able to perceive the passage of time accurately while in space.
While he was running, were you keeping track of his time?
さっきあんた トラックで
数えてたの？ヒビトのタイム｡
うん｡数えてたよ｡
Yeah, I was.
《なんだよ スゲー人気者じゃん》
Man, he's really popular...
いいな～｡
Lucky him...
《数えてたって？
ウソつけ コノヤロー》
Keeping track?
Don't lie to me!
どう？
ムッちゃんもやってみない？
Well?
You wanna give it a shot?
おっ おうっ！今度な！
S-Sure!
Some other time.
Hibito, shouldn't you be heading to the TV station?
ヒビト そろそろテレビ局に
出かける時間じゃない？
テレビ？
TV?
今夜のトークショーに
出演すんのよ｡
He's going to be on a talk show tonight.
広く国民に 自分達の仕事の意味を
伝えるのも➡
As an astronaut, one of his assignments is to explain the significance of his job to the country.
宇宙飛行士の重要な任務なわけ｡
Just how popular is he?
《どんだけ人気もんだよ…》
[TV]♪～
Now, who will our guest be tonight?
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)さあ 今夜のゲストは
誰かな？➡
今 サムライボーイと言えば
もう誰だかわかるよね？
I'm sure that most people recognize the nickname "Samurai Boy."
ワン！
わかるね｡
I already know that.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
日本人宇宙飛行士
ミスター ヒビト･ナンバ！
The Japanese astronaut, Mr. Hibito Nanba!
[TV]さて ミスター ヒビト➡
Well, Mr. Hibito...
巷では 君はサムライボーイで
通ってるけど➡
I believe that you are known to the public as Samurai Boy,
今日は 何て呼べば
いいかな？
but what would you like me to call you today?
[TV]別に何でもいいよ｡
ヒビトでも ナンバでも｡➡
Whatever you want.
Hibito or Nanba.
日本じゃ 頭のてっぺんが山みたい
だし 栗にも似てるからって➡
Since my hair's pointy and shaped like a chestnut, people in Japan called me "Mont Blanc", on occasion.
｢モンブラン｣って
呼ばれたこともあるけどね｡
う…ウケてんじゃねえか｡
H-He's actually a hit.
《あんのヤロー すげえなあ｡
アメリカで…何だ？この差は》
The guy's doing great
in America...
Why is there such a huge difference?
《ああ わかってるさ…｡➡
Yeah, I know.
あいつは いつだって涼しい顔して
弱音ひとつ吐かないんだ…➡
He's always composed, and he never complains.
そして自分の目標に向かって
惜しまず黙々と努力を重ね➡
He keeps his mouth shut, all the while working toward his goal.
着実に前進してゆく》
He's always moving forward.
《現代のサムライか…》
A modern samurai, huh?
《日々人がサムライなら…
オレ 何だ？》
If Hibito's a samurai,
what does that make me?
《オレは引き立て役…➡
I'm just his foil.
柿ピーん中の
ピーナッツぐらいなもんか…》
Like a single persimmon nut...
[TV]ええ 兄がいます｡今
宇宙飛行士を目指してんですよ｡
Yes, I have an older brother.
He's trying to become an astronaut.
Huh?
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)へえ それは素晴らしい｡
[TV]きっとなってくれると
思いますよ｡
Oh, that's wonderful.
I know he'll make it.
Wha-What?!
何言ってんだよ お前！
全米に向けて！
What do you think you're telling the American people?!
[TV]皆は知らないんだけど
実はすごい人で…➡
Most people don't know this, but he's incredible.
Yeah, I'm really proud to be his brother.
そうですね 自慢の兄です｡
バカヤロー！ほめんなよ～！
ピーナッツ兄を!!
Idiot!
Don't put your nutty brother on a pedestal!
お前…もしオレが
試験に落ちても➡
Will you still
claim you're proud to be my brother, even if I fail the exam?
自慢の兄がいるなんて
言えんのかよ…｡
[ｹｲﾀｲ](後輩)ああ 南波先輩！
僕です お久しぶりです｡
Hello?
Oh, Nanba?
It's me. We haven't talked in a while.
[ｹｲﾀｲ]やあ 君か…
どう？いい車作ってる？
Oh, it's you.
Well? You make any good cars?
それどころじゃないですよ！
That doesn't matter!
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡの人が 会社に
電話してきたんですよ！それで…｡
Someone from JAXA called our company.
And then...
え？…何？
まてら
[ｹｲﾀｲ](後輩)間寺役員が南波先輩の
こと まだ根に持ってて｡
Huh? What?
Director Matera still holds a grudge...
その電話であることないこと
ＪＡＸＡにブチまけたんですよ｡➡
He told JAXA all kinds of stories, some true and some false.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](後輩)
例の頭突きのことに加えて…➡
He even said that the headbutt incident
｢南波は宇宙飛行士に向いてない｣
とまで…｡
proved that you aren't fit to become an astronaut.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](後輩)
もしもし 先輩？聞いてますか？
先輩？➡
Hello? I can't hear you.
Are you listening?
Are you there?
Hello?
となると やはり最後の１人は
沢木君で決まりですかね？
This means our final candidate
will be Sawaki.
う～ん…暴力沙汰というのは
どうもねえ｡
We can't ignore a history of violence...
(星加)はい 星加と申します｡
宇宙航空研究開発機構の｡➡
Yes, my name is Hoshika.
I'm with the Aerospace Exploration Agency.
Is there anyone there who
以前 そちらにお勤めだった
南波六太さんと➡
might be familiar with Mr. Nanba Mutta, one of your former employees?
親交の深い方は
おられますでしょうか？
はい…ええ そうです 設計部の｡
はい｡
Yes.
Yes, that's right.
The design department...
Yes.
(教師)は～い！ちゃんと２列に
並んで下さ～い！
Okay!
Form two lines!
ええ…はい｡
Yes...
Right.
なっ！あはは｡
Come on, kids. No pushing.
はい そこ！押さない押さない｡
ちゃんと並ぶ！
Stay in line.
はい ありがとうございました｡
Yes, thank you very much.
は～い それでは
スペースドームに入場しま～す！
All right, we'll be entering the space dome now!
あっ!?おいおい これ
あさってじゃん ＩＳＳ(ｱｲｴｽｴｽ)！
Oh! The ISS will be visible the day after tomorrow.
えっ!?ホントだ！19時24分｡
Huh?
See the ISS!
The International Space Station (ISS) is currently being constructed
in space. If conditions are right, you can see it with the naked eye
during the two hours before sunrise and the two hours after sunset.
Look for the International Space Station!
You're right!
At 7:24 PM...
ぎょうかく
東北東に仰角８１度だって｡
East-northeast 81 degrees.
We don't want to miss this.
こりゃ 見逃すワケには
いかんなっ！
１９時にアラーム セットしとこ！
I'll set my alarm for 7 PM...
Oh, there she is.
お～来た｡はじまる はじまる…｡
It's about to start...
(ガイド)皆様 ＪＡＸＡツアーへ
ようこそ｡
I would like to welcome everyone to the JAXA tour.
とう　つくば
まずは 当筑波宇宙センターの
がいよう
概要について…｡
First, I will introduce Tsukuba Space Center.
Everyone?
｢みなさま｣って…｡
俺らしかいないよ お姉さん｡
We're the only ones here, lady.
えと 皆様 ＪＡＸＡは…
ＪＡＸＡは宇宙と…えと…｡
Ah, JAXA is...
JAXA is the...
Um...
新人だな この人｡
She must be new.
Uh-huh.
え～ ＪＡＸＡは
宇宙環境の利用と人工衛星の…｡
Um, JAXA is involved in aerospace and artificial satellites...
がんばれ エミちゃん
負けちゃダメ！
Hang in there, Emi.
Don't give up.
(星加)また来てんのか？あの２人｡
Those kids are back again?
まったく…平日だっていうのに｡
Seriously... It's a weekday.
しきち
ＪＡＸＡの敷地面積は 約…
え～ 約…｡
The JAXA facility covers...
Ah...
Covers...
５３万平方メートルで➡
530,000 square meters, which is big enough to house twelve Tokyo Domes.
実に東京ドームが
１２個も入るんです！
台本 覚えてんのか？あいつら｡
そうなんですよ～｡
They've memorized the script?
That's right.
ガイドより先に
言っちゃうんですよ あの子達｡
They can recite before the guide does.
ああいうのが将来 宇宙飛行士に
なったりすんだよな～｡➡
Those kids are the ones who end up becoming astronauts...
困ったもんだね ハハハハ…｡
Funny stuff.
JAXA seeks to build a secure and prosperous society,
ＪＡＸＡは宇宙航空の
さらなる可能性を追求し➡
豊かな社会へ貢献します｡
by utilizing aerospace technology.
それがＪＡＸＡの使命 人類共通の
知的資産の拡大を図り➡
JAXA's mission is to expand upon the collective knowledge
たゆまぬ進化とともに…｡
あ…え～｡
of the human race.
Um, er...
それでは これよりＤＶＤを
ご覧いただきます！
Next, we have a video for you to watch.
Oh, right!
あ はい！えっ あれ？えっ？
Eh, huh?
What?
現在
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)何ぼんやりしてんの？
Don't space out.
Here's your ticket.
はい チケット｡あんたの分｡
I have a pass.
私はパス持ってるからね｡
あ…サンキュー｡
Oh, thank you.
失くすなよ～｡
Get your shit together, man...
《私達兄弟にとって…ＪＡＸＡは
｢第二の学校｣だった》
The two of us thought of JAXA
like a second school.
We kept track of every presentation
《ＪＡＸＡの宇宙飛行士や
研究者達の講演会などは➡
given by a JAXA astronaut or scientist.
くまなくチェックし
行ける時には ほとんど行った…》
We attended
as many as we could.
《その中で…
あれは誰だったかな？➡
In particular,
there was this one guy...
頭髪が すげえ
フサフサしてる人が言った》
Some guy with flowing hair.
(星加)宇宙飛行士に
なれる人っていうのは➡
It takes more than just skill to become an astronaut.
その資質だけじゃなく 実は強い
｢運｣を持ち合わせているんです｡➡
You must also have luck on your side.
残念ながら 私には
その｢運｣がありませんでした｡
I'm sorry to say that I wasn't one of the lucky ones.
現在
《運か…》
Luck, huh?
《合格基準を満たす人が
数人いるならば➡
If there are multiple people who qualify,
they'll pick the ones without any skeletons in their closets.
過去に汚点の少ない者が
選ばれるだろう…》
《頭突きの話が間寺役員
本人の口から➡
If Director Matera told JAXA about the headbutting,
ＪＡＸＡに
伝わったということは…➡
もう１００％ 救いはない…》
I'm 100% screwed.
《俺にも どうやら…
｢運｣はなかった》
Guess I wasn't one of the lucky ones, either.
Next, please.
(係員)次の方 どうぞ！
あの～大丈夫ですか？あの人｡
Uh,
is he okay?
He's perfectly fine.
だいじょぶ だいじょぶ
緊張してるだけだから｡
He's just nervous.
((じゃあ 約束な))
Then it's a promise.
《なんて言ったらいいんだろう…
日々人に…》
What am I supposed to tell Hibito?
(係員)それじゃあ 行きますよ～！
Okay, it's ready to start.
Go, go!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)((楽しみにしてる))
I can't wait to see it happen.
《シャロンに
何て言ったらいいっ!!》
What am I supposed to tell Sharon?
《ちっくしょおぉ～っ！》
Damn it!
兄弟とか 親のこととかまで➡
Sometimes, he'd even insult your siblings or parents.
平気で悪く言っちゃう
人なんですよ その…➡
That's the kind of person Director Matera is.
That's who Nanba headbutted.
南波先輩に頭突きを食らった
間寺っていう上司は｡
なるほど｡
I see.
(後輩)僕には南波先輩のように➡
I wasn't brave enough to headbutt him the way Nanba did.
頭突きする勇気は
ないんですけど 正直➡
But I certainly wanted to, once or twice.
それぐらいの気持ちに
なったことはあります｡
(ｳｪｲﾄﾚｽ)アメリカンおふたつ➡
Two coffees and one espresso.
ブレンドおひとつ 580円です｡
Your total is 580 yen.
ここは私が｡
(後輩達)あ すいません！
I got this.
Oh, thank you.
いやいや こちらこそ
ご協力 ありがとうございます｡
No problem.
I want to thank you for your help.
これで 何とか掛け合ってみます｡
420円のお返しになります｡
This will give me a talking point to use.
Your change is 420 yen.
ありがとう｡
(ｳｪｲﾄﾚｽ)ありがとうございました｡
Thank you.
Have a nice day.
(後輩)あの…｡
Excuse me...
南波先輩って
よく わからない人ですけど➡
Nanba was always an enigma to me...
もし あの人が
宇宙飛行士になったら➡
But were he to become an astronaut,
多分…
なんか納得しちゃいそうです｡
I wouldn't be too surprised!
それも録音しときゃよかった｡
I should have recorded that statement, as well.
《弟のために頭突きか…
変わってね～んだな 昔から…》
Headbutted his superior for his brother's sake, huh?
He hasn't changed.
びゃああ～！うう～！
どうした？ボーズ｡
What's wrong, kid?
うう～ころんだぁ～！
I fell down...
そうか ははっ…君は地球に
頭突きしたわけだな｡
I see.
That means you headbutted the Earth.
Headbutted?
ズツキぃ？ズツキってぇ？
What does that mean?
Back when
《昔…俺の髪が
まだフサフサだった頃➡
I still had flowing hair,
あの兄弟がＪＡＸＡに
入りびたっていた｡➡
those brothers spent all their time at JAXA.
俺は１人を｢モジャ君｣➡
I nicknamed one "Afro",
１人を｢ツン君｣と
名付けてやった》
and the other one "Spike".
ん？どうした モジャ君？
その おでこ｡
Hmm?
What happened to your forehead, Afro?
あ…ケガした｡
Oh, I got hurt.
ケガ？
Hurt?
いろいろあるんだよ
１３にもなると｡
A thirteen-year-old has a lot to deal with.
アレね 頭突きしたんだよ
僕のために｡
Actually,
he headbutted someone for my sake.
頭突き？
Headbutted?
ほんとのこと言うと
相手のいじめっ子より➡
Honestly, I was stronger than those bullies.
僕のほうが強いんだけどね｡➡
ムッちゃんは
僕の前に立つんだよ｡
But Mu stood in front of me.
Hey, Hibito...
((あのな 日々人
お前は手ぇ出すな｡➡
You stay out of this.
You're too strong!
強ぇ～んだから｡
ほんとに強ぇ～奴はな➡
People who are truly strong don't need to fight.
手を出さないんだよ｡
だから お前はガマンしろ))
So suck it up.
((いつまで
おしゃべりしてんだよ！))
Hey!
Enough chitchat!
((ムカつく奴いたら
代わりに兄ちゃんがなっ！))
If someone hassles you,
your brother will step in!
((頭 出してやるっ!!))
And use his head!
なるほど｡
I understand.
現在
バイバーイ！
(星加)バイバーイ！
Bye-bye...
Bye-bye.
(星加)《南波六太…実力はある｡➡
Nanba Mutta...
He has the ability.
才能も多分ある》
He probably has the talent.
《元々 南波君の方が
優位だったのに…➡
He's a strong candidate,
過去のあやまちが
ねじれ伝わったせいで➡
but if he's dropped because of one mistake in his past,
不合格になってしまったら…➡
運がなかったとしか
言いようがない…》
then he isn't one of the lucky ones.
《それじゃあ
俺と おんなじじゃないか》
That would make him just like me.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](二村)はい 二村です｡
Hello, this is Nimura.
俺だ 二村君｡南波君の件だが➡
Nimura, it's me.
I'm calling about Nanba. He still has a chance.
まだ可能性はある｡
手伝って欲しい｡
I need your help.
はい…はい わかりました｡➡
Yes...
Yes, I understand.
やってみましょう 星加さん｡
Let's give it a shot, Hoshika.
(星加)《六太君 君は全く
気付いていないだろう｡➡
Mutta,
you probably haven't realized it yet.
あの時のツン君が
宇宙飛行士となり…➡
Spike grew up to be an astronaut.
そして あのモジャ君が
十数年ぶりに 俺の前に現れた》
And then,
for the first time in over a decade,
Afro showed up, too.
《そうさ…俺の心は…
ずっと踊りっぱなしなんだ!!》
Yep,
all this time,
I've been dancing a jig in my heart.
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#07 Dear Hibito
＜ムッちゃん
宇宙飛行士審査は？＞
Mu, how did the test go?
＜どうせ わかることだから
先に言っておく＞
Since I already know the result, I'll tell you up-front.
I have a 92% chance of failing.
＜９２％ 俺 落ちた｡
俺には 運はないんだ＞
My luck is terrible.
Wasn't going to space your dream?
＜宇宙 行くの 夢なんだろ？
諦めんなよ＞
Don't give up!
＜もし諦め切れるんなら
そんなもん 夢じゃねえ！＞
If you can give up,
then it wasn't really your dream!
Meanwhile, I find myself caught up in some serious business overseas.
＜そんな中 俺は異国の地で➡
とんでもない事件に
巻き込まれる＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Dear Hibito."
＜俺は 何かと不運に縁がある＞
I have plenty of bad luck.
パンパカパーン！
今週の➡
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
宇宙写真で～す！
すっげえ！
Awesome!